{"tossups": [{"question": "As part of Operation PANDORA, this organization tried to stir up anti-Semitism by mailing out racist fake pamphlets of right-wing Jewish organizations to civil rights organizations. This organization, which often collaborated with GRU, was led by Vladimir Kryuchkov, who helped plan an August 1991 coup. During the fall of the Berlin Wall, thousands of this organization\u2019s files were burned by its officers, including Vladimir Putin. For ten points, name this Soviet intelligence agency.", "answer": "<b> KGB</b> (or<b> Komitet Gosudarstvennoy Bezopasnosti</b>; accept<b> Committee for State Security</b>) (2) In 1894, kids accidentally started a fire under the stands in this city\u2019s South End Grounds during a baseball game; the stadium and over 100 buildings were destroyed in the ensuing Great Roxbury Fire. This city lost over 60 acres worth of buildings in 12 hours after a warehouse on Kingston Street caught fire in 1872; that event was commemorated by its resident poet, Oliver Wendell Holmes Senior. In 1919, 21 people died after a storage tank burst and released a flood of molasses in, for ten points, what Massachusetts city? ANSWER:<b> Boston</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A student of this university named Sadie Tanner Mossell Alexander was the first African American woman to receive a Ph.D. A machine known as the \u201cGiant Brain\u201d was created at this university to calculate artillery firing tables; that early computer was ENIAC. The oldest medical school created in America is this university\u2019s Perelman School, and it is also home to the first school of business, which is named after Joseph Wharton. For ten points, name this university founded by Benjamin Franklin in Philadelphia.", "answer": "University of<b> Pennsylvania</b> (accept U<b>Penn</b>; do not accept Penn State)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This artist painted his friend Adrianus Jacobus Zuyderland dressed in blue with his head in his hands in<em> At Eternity\u2019s Gate</em>, which shares its name with a 2018 film about this man. A landscape painting by this artist depicts a cypress tree and a crescent moon over the town of Saint-Remy. This artist of<em> The</em> <em>Potato Eaters</em> was hospitalized in Arles after injuring himself with a razor in 1888. For ten points, name this Dutch artist of<em> Starry Night</em> and<em> Self Portrait with Bandaged Ear</em>.", "answer": "Vincent (Willem)<b> van Gogh</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man rose to power after scheming with the Comte de Chevigny [comt de sheh-vi-nee] to remove Fran\u00b8cois de Noyers [fran-swah de no-yay]. The League of the Rhine was formed by this man to limit Austrian power. This man concluded a war with Spain through the Treaty of the Pyrenees. This advisor barely survived a coup during the Fronde. For ten points, name this cardinal who acted as minister for Louis XIII and regent for Louis XIV.", "answer": "Cardinal Jules<b> Mazarin</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a series of documents related to this scandal, William Rehnquist was referred to as \u201cRenchburg;\u201dthe existence of those documents was publicly revealed by Alexander Butterfield. John Mitchell served 19 months in prison for his role in this scandal, which included Robert Bork\u2019s agreement to fire special prosecutor Archibald Cox during the Saturday Night Massacre. The \u201cSmoking Gun\u201d tape was a key piece of evidence in, for ten points, what scandal that ended with Richard Nixon\u2019s resignation?", "answer": "<b> Watergate</b> scandal", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "After this event, William Graham was criticized for memorializing members of the 5th Artillery who were killed on a dynamite-laced bridge while en route to stop this event. A rally to drum up support for this event was held at Blue Island, and it occurred despite an injunction from Richard Olney. When this event was deemed to interfere with federal mail, Grover Cleveland stepped in to end it. For ten points, name this 1894 Chicago strike against a namesake railway company.", "answer": "<b> Pullman</b> Strike", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The phrase \u201cpig in the python\u201d titled a cultural history of this group, which was collectively named <em>Time</em> Person of the Year in 1966. Reduced adult supervision led this group\u2019s successor to be called the\u201clatchkey generation.\u201d Lower mortgage requirements and the G.I. bill contributed to the rise of, for ten points, what American generation that was succeeded by Generation X and was born after World War II?", "answer": "<b> Baby Boom</b>ers", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This site was once believed to have been imported from Africa for use in healing, then transported from Mount Killaraus after a long battle. In 1915, this site was sold for 6000 pounds to Cecil Chubbs, who then donated it. This site is surrounded by \u201caubrey holes\u201d speculated to have once contained bluestones; earlier historians speculated this site was a center of Druidic worship. For ten points, name this prehistoric site near Salisbury consisting of standing rocks.", "answer": "<b> Stonehenge</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "At a 1993 auction, a dummy named Ivan that was meant to test conditions prior to this man\u2019s most famous undertaking sold for nearly $200,000. A cedar tree inspired the most famous callsign of this man, who exclaimed \u201cPoyekhali!\u201d In 1968, this man died while flying a MiG-15 after an air traffic controller misreported the weather, according to declassified files. After a mission of less than two hours in 1961, this man parachuted back to Earth. For ten points, name this cosmonaut who, aboard<em> Vostok 1</em>, became the first man in space.", "answer": "Yuri Alekseyevich<b> Gagarin</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This dynasty\u2019s general Meng Tian defeated the Xiongnu [shee-ong-nu]. An attempt to assassinate a ruler of this dynasty involved putting lead at the end of a lute. This dynasty,</b> <b>whose chancellor (+)</b> <b>Li Si instituted Legalist policies, was led by a man who supposedly</b> <b>drank an \u201celixir of life\u201d that was just mercury. This dynasty, which followed the (*)</b> Warring States Period, was replaced by the Han Dynasty. A terracotta army was built for a ruler of, for ten points, what dynasty in which the Great Wall was built under the rule of Shi Huangdi?", "answer": "<b> Qin</b> [chin] Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this musical piece that Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart believed he was composing for his own funeral.", "answer": "Mozart\u2019s<b> Requiem</b> mass in D minor (prompt on mass)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Members of this irregular fighting force often used the \u201cone slow, four quick\u201d doctrine. Eddie Adams photographed a captain in this group who had recently killed a Lieutenant Colonel and his family; in that photo, the member of this group is wearing a flannel shirt</b> <b>and (+)</b> <b>shot at point blank range by General Nguyen Loan [when loan]. This group led</b> <b>multiple attacks in January (*)</b> 1968, striking the city of Hue [hway] and breaching the U.S. embassy in Saigon. For ten points, name this guerrilla fighting group that fought against the U.S. and South Vietnam during the Tet Offensive.", "answer": "<b> Viet Cong</b> (or<b> N</b>ational<b> L</b>iberation<b> F</b>ront) Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>While Aristophanes of Byzantium led one of these facilities, he invented the diacritical marks used in the Greek language; Aristarchus of Samothrace later led that one of these</b> <b>facilities. When one of these facilities was excavated in (+)</b> <b>Ashurbanipal\u2019s palace, its</b> <b>discoveries were mixed with tablets found in Sennacherib\u2019s palace, rendering the true discovery location of the (*)</b><em> Epic of Gilgamesh</em> a mystery. For ten points, name this type of location that Julius Caesar burned in Alexandria, causing the loss of thousands of papyrus scrolls and their educational contents.", "answer": "ancient<b> library</b> (accept<b> Library of Alexandria</b>; accept<b> Library</b> of Ashurbanipal after his name is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>The president who authorized this agreement wrote a letter outlining his diplomatic strategy to Governor James Gerrard of Kentucky. Fran\u00b8cois de Barb\u00b4e-Marbois [bar-bay</b> <b>mar-bwah] was a key negotiator of this agreement, which arose after an (+)</b> <b>insurrection</b> <b>on Saint Domingue [sahn doh-meeng]. Talleyrand objected to this plan, which resulted in the (*) </b> Lewis and Clark Expedition surveying its central land area. The size of the United States was doubled by, for ten points, what 1803 purchase of French land under Thomas Jefferson?", "answer": "<b> Louisiana Purchase</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The weekly Torah reading is divided into this many aliyahs. In the first part of the book of Revelation, the author writes letters to this many churches in Asia Minor. Jericho\u2019s (+) walls fell after this many days of marching, and King David had this many brothers. The Passover feast lasts this many days, and this is the number of (*) </b> lamps on the Temple of Jerusalem\u2019s menorah. For ten points, give this number of the day God rested in the first Genesis narrative, which is also the number of deadly sins.", "answer": "<b> seven</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s deformed son was sent to the monastery of Pr\u00a8um after his plot to overthrow this man was discovered. This man\u2019s mother Bertrada assisted him in his struggle against his brother, and he divorced his (+) Lombard wife Desiderata before conquering Italy. This ruler, who put down the Great Saxon Revolt after converting them to Christianity, had his forces defeated at the Battle of (*)</b> Roncevaux Pass, the source of the<em> Song of Roland</em>. For ten points, name this Frankish king crowned Emperor of the Romans on Christmas Day 800.", "answer": "<b> Charlemagne</b> Page 10", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>An invasion of this country was halted at the Battle of the Tennis Court, part of an engagement at Kohima. A pretender provisional government for this country was set up in Singapore, after attempts to ally it with the Axis led to the exile of (+) Subhas Bose. A \u201cQuit [this country]\u201d Movement demanded independence for this country before it sent aid for World War II, though the (*)</b> Muslim League was willing to contribute troops. For ten points, name this modern-day country from which the British Raj conscripted soldiers against the wishes of Mohandas Gandhi.", "answer": "<b> India</b> (accept descriptions of British-controlled<b> India</b>, including British<b> Raj</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}